<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of that which hath bin written in the questions of the ignorant ministerie, and the communicating with them. By Iohn Penri</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836991</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836991</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1295</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1295)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 969:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of that which hath bin written in the questions of the ignorant ministerie, and the communicating with them. By Iohn Penri</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[East Molesey :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption on B1r; imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Answers STC 22908: Robert Some.  A godly treatise containing and deciding certaine questions, moved of late in London and other places, touching the ministerie, sacraments, and Church.</note>
                  <note>"Apparently no preliminary leaves printed."--Folger Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of I4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Some, Robert, 1542-1609. --  Godly treatise containing and deciding certaine questions, moved of late in London and other places, touching the ministerie, sacraments, and Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1295:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1295:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A defence of that which hath bin written in the queſtions of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant miniſterie, and the communicating with them. By IOHN PENRI.</head>
            <p>THere bee two thinges (M. D. <hi>Some</hi>) wherein you by oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that trueth which out of the worde of God I had ſette downe, concerning the two former queſtions, haue beene wanting both vnto your ſelfe and to the cauſe; the defence whereof you vndertook. The former want of the 2. appeareth by your ſpare dealing in a matter of ſuch great waight; wherein you haue dealt with ſo illiberall a hande, that what hath bin written by you, might ſeem to proceed rather from any, then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man whoſe giftes and learning ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to promiſe the affordinge, of greater and more waightie matters, then any ſet downe in that treatiſe.</p>
            <p>The nomber of my reſons were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, you onely haue touched 2. of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the reſt are not dealt with. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cauſe as yet remaineth whol. For be it you had aunſwered theſe 2.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1295:2"/>as you haue not, yet had you not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the doutful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of thoſe that know not in theſe points which way to turn them, as long as any one of my reaſons remained vnanſwered.</p>
            <p>In this point there is alſo another want, which I would had bin redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And that is of two ſorts. Firſt, a manifeſt going from the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; For the queſtion being, whether ignorant men, not ordained of God for the gatheringe together of the Saints, be miniſters or no; you leaue that, and prooue the Sacraments ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by them, viz. by popiſhe prieſts, and our dumbe miniſters in the daies of blindnes and ignorance to be ſacraments, which is no part of the matter in controuerſie, but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point to be diſcuſſed (if men will be gotten at all to enter therevnto) when the former is determined and decided.</p>
            <p>Secondly, your reaſons are ſo few, &amp; ſo commonly knowen vnto all, that for their nomber, a ſmall deate of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per might containe an anſwere vnto
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1295:2"/>them, for their noueltie, they coulde not put a man that had accordinge vnto knowledge, but once allowed of the cauſe, to anye great labour in anſwering them. As being things ſo commonly obiected by all, learned or vnlearned, that holde our readers to be miniſters, and thinke it lawfull to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with them, as by courſ of ſpech they fal vnto that diſcourſe, wher al men may eaſily ſee, that there was a great ouerſight committed by M. SOME, in deeming that the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning of a cauſe countenanced by moſt of the godly learned, would be taken in hand by any, who could not anſwere the reaſons which he might be ſure would be obiected by al. And who could be ignorant, that the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous controuerſie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of baptiſme, both by popiſh prieſts &amp; our dumb miniſters, would offer it ſelfe in the forefront to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the trueth? that the ciuill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie, the miniſterie of the dumbe Leuites, the corrupt outward calling of our readers woulde require an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1295:3"/>which are the reaſons, and the onely reaſons vſed by you.</p>
            <p>The laſt want I finde in you, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the inſufficiency of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which euidently ſhew the inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, that would be inferred by them. Your reſons are all of them faultie, eyther becauſe they deſire that for granted which is the queſtion, or make thoſe things of like nature, wherin there is a gret diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimilitude. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt of the 2. falts it commeth to paſſe, that you take for granted, that the writings of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende and godly men, as of Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, M. Beza, &amp;c. will prooue that, which the word of the eternall God doth not warrant. Hence you take it graunted, that popiſh prieſts were miniſters: that the outwarde appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Churche maketh a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; that whenſoeuer the word of inſtitution is pronounced with the outward element, ther muſt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a Sacrament, that I take an euill miniſter for no miniſter; that there was a nullity both of Caiphas his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1295:3"/>becauſe he came in by bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and of the litigious miniſters in the Church of Philippi, &amp;c. How ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you take thoſe things as granted principles,<note place="margin">1. Phil. 1.15.</note> yet they are the points in controuerſie, and ſo far from beeing yelded vnto by me, that I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed euery one of them to be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe.</p>
            <p>The diſsimilitude is in the reaſons drawn from the Leuitical prieſthood, and the ciui magiſtracie, with whom if you compare the miniſtery of the new couenaunt, you ſhall finde, firſte that you bring in a ſimilitude to ſhew that whiche is not prooued; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that you make thoſe to bee twinnes, which all men muſt needes graunt to be as vnlike, as crooked &amp; ſtraight lines are vnmatchable.</p>
            <p>And thus much I thought needfull generally to ſet downe concerninge your manner of dealing: Not that I wold any way diſgrace, you who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, for that is no part of mine intent, the Lorde is my witnes. Nay, I would be loth to let that ſyllable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1295:4"/>me, that might giue you or any els the leaſt occaſion in the world, to thinke that I carrye any other heart towards you, then I ought to beare towards a reuerend learned man fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God. And howſoeuer, vnles you alter your iudgment, I can neuer agre with you in theſe pointes; becauſe I am aſſured you ſwarue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth: yet this diſagreement ſhalbe ſo farre from making a breach of that bonde of loue, wherewith in the Lord I am tyed vnto you, that I doubt not, but we ſhalbe at one in that day, when al of vs ſhall be at vnitie in him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth one and the ſelfe-ſame for euer.</p>
            <p>Now I am to come to your booke, from the 20. page whereof, vnto the 28. laying the foundation of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you vſe againſt mee, to prooue the lawfulnes of communicatinge with dum miniſters, you handle two neadles points. Firſt that they which were baptized by popiſh prieſts, haue receiued true baptim as touching the ſubſtance. Secondly that they are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1295:4"/>the ſacramentes of baptiſme and the holy ſupper of the Lorde, which are deliuered in the Church of England by vnpreching miniſters. In theſe two pointes M. <hi>Some,</hi> you haue prooued nothing that my writinges haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; but you haue quickened a dead controuerſie, not vnlikely to giue the wrangling ſpirits of this age, cauſe to breed greater ſturres in the Church. I ſee no other effect, which the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of theſe queſtions can bringe foorth but this. And it is to be feared that the ſlendernes of the reaſons v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your booke, to prooue that which you haue vndertaken to ſhew; will geeue occaſion vnto mannie, whoe of them-ſelues are too too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to iangle, to doubt of that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of before they made no queſtion. So that by ſeeking to ſtay the courſe of a needful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie, you haue both giuen it a larger paſſage, and opened the doore vnto a queſtion very fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in our time. you know I deale in neither of theſe pointes. If you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtayed from entring into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1295:5"/>that are very odious, and more impertinent vnto the matter in hand: it were good that the church were further and more ſoundly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied by you in theſe 2. pointes, which you alone in our Churche haue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likly called in queſtion. And for mine owne parte, when you haue done, I know not who will be your aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I ſee no reaſon whie I ſhould deal in controuerſies of ſo ſmal gaine. Of this I am aſſured, that neyther po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſts, nor any other ignoraunt guides are miniſters. whether the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment adminiſtred by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or no, look you to that, which haue in your treatiſe debated that, which my writings neuer called into queſtion. If you wil needs proue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be miniſters, becauſe you can not get me to denie that which hath bene adminiſtred to be a ſacrament, you ſhall but preſſe that which will prooue nothing. Your reaſon is, as if you ſhoulde ſaye, that eyther all they which ſupplie the places of miniſters are miniſters, or els an inconuenience
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1295:5"/>is likely to follow. A ſtrange manner of demonſtration, Gods ordinaunce muſt needs be thruſt out of the dores becauſe an inconuenience would be likely to enſue the admittinge of it. The cauſe will not be thus anſwered at your hands; and I am ſorie that a man ſo reuerende in mine eyes, hath dealt ſo vnſubſtantially in a matter belonging to the ſeruice of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God: the ſlenderneſſe of the reaſon is apparant. In the latter ende of the booke I haue farther ſhewed the ſame; thither I am to referre you and the reader.</p>
            <p>Now I coulde well ouerpaſſe theſe two pointes, becauſe of them-ſelues they containe nothing that I haue withſtoode: But in as muche as you haue not onely grounded them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe principles, and ſuch as in no wiſe can be warraunted by the canon of the word, but alſo inferre vpon their grant, that our readers are miniſters, and conſequently, that it is no ſinne to communicate with them. I am firſt to ſet downe the ſtate of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1295:6"/>which in deed is and ought to be decided betweene you and me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the elemente adminiſtred, both by popiſh prieſts, and other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching miniſters: and ſecondly to examine the groundes whereby you prooue the element alreadie deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them to be a ſacrament, which you know I do not denie to be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And this is the point that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth our ſtate ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the other.</note>The queſtion therefore is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one or the other of them haue deliuered a ſacrament in reſpect of the action done; but whether a chriſtian going vnto them for thoſe holy ſeales, may be aſſured, that hee can receiue the ſame at their handes. I affirme that wee can not; M. <hi>Some</hi> taketh it graunted that we may; my warrant is out of the worde, becauſe there is no promiſe made to vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that the action celebrated by ſuch men, is a ſacramentall action, and where there is no promiſe, there can bee no aſſuraunce, becauſe our aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ariſeth onely of fayth, whiche muſt be grounded vpon the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſet downe in the word; wee haue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1295:6"/>no promiſe that they can deliuer vs a ſacrament, becauſe they are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. For they onely are enioyned by our Sauiour Chriſt to deliuer a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Matth. 28.18.19.</note> neither do we know what hee can deliuer which is no miniſter.</p>
            <p>So that the queſtion is now growne to this iſſue, whether popiſh prieſtes and our vnpreachinge miniſters, bee miniſters or no; whom if I can proue to be none, then the matter is cleare, that no man going vnto them for the ſacrament, can aſſure himſelfe there to haue the ſame. And this ſhall be a generall reaſon, equally belonginge vnto both the pointes handeled by you, the particulars whereof ſhal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in their places.</p>
            <list>
               <head>That no popishe prieſt therefore is a miniſter.</head>
               <item>1 Euery miniſter muſt be at the leaſt by profeſsion, a member of the true Church. No popiſh priſt is by profeſsion a member of the true Church. Therfore no popiſh prieſt is a miniſter.</item>
               <item>2 Euery miniſter hath an office with in the bodie of the Churche. No
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1295:7"/>popiſhe prieſt hath an office with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bodie of the Church. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no popiſh prieſt is a miniſter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The propoſitions or firſt part of both theſe reaſons are ſet downe euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainely by the wiſedome of God, in theſe wordes. For as we haue many members in one bodie,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.4 5.6.</note> and all members haue not one office; ſo we being many, are one bodie in Chriſt, and euerye one an others members, ſeeing then that we haue giftes that are diuers. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The place ſheweth cleerly, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not a member, is not of the bodie, if not of the body, then no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. A gaine, whoſoeuer is no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he hath no office in the bodie; if no office, no miniſter. He that ſhould obiect that in this place is mente a member of the bodie, by election in the ſecret counſell of God, and not in the acknowledgemente of the Church by profeſsion, would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the anſwering, Becauſe it is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and not election, that maketh ſuch a member in the church as may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1295:7"/>haue an office therein; of which ſort the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in this place. by vocation, I meane that whereof the holy ghoſte ſpeaketh, where it is ſaid, Many are called, but few are choſen:<note place="margin">Matth. 20.10.</note> neither can any man denie him to be a member of the Churche, which by outward profeſsion ſubmitteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto true religion, and ſuch are the members, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">To be a member ſo the true Church is one thing, and to bee a true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church is another thing.</note> namely ſuch as are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers in the iudgement of the Church, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das was a member in the iudgement of the Churche, though not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to election. A further proofe of the propoſitions you ſhall find. 1. cor. 12.26.28. Hee was no prieſt in the olde teſtament, that was not a Iewe by profeſſion; yea, and of the line of Aaron to: and ſhall he be accounted a miniſter amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, that is a ſtranger from the profeſsion of the trueth, &amp; a profeſſed Idolater? Iſhmael &amp; Eſau, were circumcized, and the ſonnes of thoſe fathers vnto whome the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt was made; Euen I will be thy God, &amp; the God of thy ſeed. They &amp;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1295:8"/>their poſterities fell from true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: well admit that the profanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ſtil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued in their houſes: yet a man ſupplying the place of a prieſt among them, was no prieſt in deed, thogh he ten thouſand times profaned circumciſion, and woulde brag neuer ſo often, that he worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped after his Idolatrous maner, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God but the God of his father Abraham, &amp; ſware onely by the feare of his father Iſaak. The reaſon herof, is, becauſe that euery prieſt vnder the law, muſt be an Iſraelite by profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is a member of the true Church, neither could any of the godly aſſure them-ſelues, that an Edomitiſhe prieſt adminiſtred true circumciſion according to the ſubſtance. Now I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a popiſh priſt no otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I would haue done of an Iſmaelitiſhe or Edomitiſh circumciſiſer; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of that ſeal of the couenant, ſtill continuing in mount Seir.</p>
            <p>Whereas in the aſſumption or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of both the reaſons, I deny popiſh prieſtes to be members of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1295:8"/>church; my meaning is not that there are none of the elect, within the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of poperie, whom the Lorde may cal in his good time: For I would not denie this vnto Mahometiſm, or that there are not left in poperie certaine rubiſhes and ſteps of true religion, for this difference I make betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other Infidels, though the Iewes alſo may claim this vnto themſelues. But I meane that the popiſh religion is ſuch a religion as whoſoeuer liueth and dyeth in the profeſſion thereof: he liueth &amp; dieth out of the Church, where ſaluation is not poſsibly to be had, for any thing that is made kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto man. Whence it neceſſarily followeth, that in poperie there is no Church. If it be obiected that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes are within the couenaunt, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as long ſince they profeſſed the trueth. Mine anſwere wil be, that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery was neuer the trueth as yet, that no papiſt in that he was a papiſt, euer profeſſed the trueth, and that God made no couenant with profeſſed I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolators, as all papiſts are.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1295:9"/>
            <p>Antichriſt I grant ſhould ſit as God in the temple of God,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.4.</note> but it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the temple of God, ſince he plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his peſtilent chaire therein. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie in deede hath inuaded the ſeats and poſſeſsions of true religion, and began firſt where the trueth was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. For the myſterie of iniquitie firſt appeared within the Churche, &amp; not elſe-where, where true religion flowriſhed, and not among the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: neyther coulde he be that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, whoſe beginning ſhoulde be in Paganiſme. But although poperie tooke roote in the ſoyle where the true Churche was planted; yet it ſo grew there, that it ſtill continued to be the ſynagogue of Sathan, &amp; could neuer as yet be the Churche of God; howſoeuer it hath ouergrowen the poſſeſsion thereof. And what though their fathers, who nowe are papiſtes, were within the couenant, as profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing true religion; ſhall it therefore followe that their Idolatrous ſonnes ſhould be ſo to: If they returne the Lorde hath mercie in ſtore for them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1295:9"/>I denie not. But what is there in this point ſaid for the papiſtes, which the Iewes cannot with far more ſhewe of reaſon pretend for themſelues? The profaning of baptiſm among the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes can make them no more to be within the Churche, then the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the profanation of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion among the Iſhmaelits &amp; Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits could keepe them under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant. And why ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>opiſh bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme any more tye the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>des coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt to an Idolatrous race, then an Iſhmaelitiſh or Edomitiſh cutting off of the foreskinne, linke him to be the God of thoſe adulterous generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Oh, but the Lorde himſelfe hath ſayd, In Iſaak ſhall thy ſeed be called,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.7. gen. 21.12. Mal. 1.2.3. rom. 9.13.</note> and Iaacob haue I loued, and hated Eſau; whie the ſame Lorde in reſpect of his reuealed wil, for with his ſecret election men muſt not meddle, hath ſaide, the profeſſors of true religion do I loue, but the Idolatrous papiſts my ſoule abhorreth; It will be heere demanded, whether I make no more account of popiſhe baptiſme, then of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1295:10"/>Edomitiſh circumciſion, I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I ſhoulde. For a circumciſed Edomite being receiued, to be a true worſhipper at Ieruſalem, ſhoulde as well content himſelfe with that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion (circumciſion being not a thing inuented by man, or don in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of man, but ordained by the Lord, and done in regarde of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant made vnto Abraham) as wee do with popiſh baptiſm, which is not called in queſtion.</p>
            <p>And yet that which is ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the profeſsion of the trueth, by the forefathers, is not altogether true in poperye; for there be many large regions nowe profeſsing pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where not ſo much as the name of Chriſt was heard, vntill they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come groſſely popiſhe. So that their firſt ſtep was out of paganiſme vnto poperye. And this is the eſtate of all thoſe poor oppreſſed vaſſals the weſt Indians, who now in great nombers profes Romiſh Idolatrie. For at ſuch time as the Spanyard inuading their land, brought vppon them the moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1295:10"/>miſerable ſlauery of bodie and ſoule, that are vpon any people vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, they had not ſo much as hearde whether there was anye Chriſte,<note place="margin">Peter. M. de rebus Occeani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Decad 4.5.</note> but were moſt hethniſh, &amp; ſenceles Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, as may appeare by the popiſhe hyſtoriographers them-ſelues, who wrote the ſtories of thoſe times. And therefore (to omit, whoſe poſterities many of the nations within Europe are, that haue refuſed the light of the Goſpell) though it were granted, that the reſt of the popiſh rable were with in the couenant; yet theſe miſerable hethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> papiſts, can be ſaid to be vnder no couenant, but that which is made vnto poperie and paganiſme, I hope M <hi>Some,</hi> howſoeuer you may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that other popiſh ſhauelings can deliuer a ſacrament, yet that you will doubt, whether any man coulde be aſſured to receiue thoſe holy ſeals at the handes of the heathen maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers remaining in Cuba, hiſpani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ola, Mexico, or any other the Eaſtern partes.</p>
            <p>And thus muche concerning the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1295:11"/>aſſumption, I am not ignoraunt that famous and worthy men,<note place="margin">M. Caluin epiſt. 103.</note> haue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe written concerning the popishe Church, and therefore I am not to be preſſed with theyr authority.</p>
            <p>I might in the 3. place vſe agaynſt you M. <hi>Some,</hi> a reaſon of your owne thus concluded. No miniſterye is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, becauſe euery miniſterye is an ordinance of God, which cannot be turned vnto ſacrileage. The popiſh priſthood is ſacriledg, as you haue ſet downe, page 21. Therfore the popiſh prieſthood is no miniſtery, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently popish prieſts are no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. You may ſee that you haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrown your owne cauſe. But this manner of reaſoninge, although it ſhould be of force againſt your ſelfe, inaſmuch as your owne wordes are brought to expreſſe your owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet I account inſufficient, my third reaſon therefore is this.</p>
            <p n="3">3 They are no miniſters whoſe very miniſterye ouerthroweth directly the prieſthood of our ſauior chriſt But the very miniſtery of popishe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1295:11"/>prieſts, directly ouerthroweth the prieſthood of Chriſte: therefore they are no miniſters.</p>
            <p>I know not what can be pretended againſt the propoſition, vnleſſe men woulde dreame of a miniſtery, wyth whom the prieſthood of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus cannot ſtande. The latter part of the reaſon is true,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.28. &amp; 10.10. 1. iohn 1.7 act. 4.12. Epheſ. 1.7. Heb. 10.12.15. and 9.26. Heb. 5.25. &amp; 10.14. &amp; 9.14.</note> if it bee true that Chriſt is the onely ſacrifice for ſinne, that he is no more to be offred, that by once offering himſelfe, he hath made full ſatisfaction for the ſinnes of the whole worlde, and that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe prieſtes dayly ſacrifice to apeaſe Gods wrath, for the ſinnes of the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they are no miniſters who are made, that is, called, elected &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Idolaters. Popiſh prieſts are called, choſen and ordained by Idolators. Therefore they are no miniſters.</p>
            <p>The propoſition appeareth in that a miniſter can be made by none, but by ſuch as vnto whom the Lord hath giuen leaue to deale in that action, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1295:12"/>the action is fruſtrate. As if a company of women, though religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and godly, ſhoulde goe about to make a miniſter, the action is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Of the aſſumption that popiſh prieſts are made by Idolators, I make no queſtion. And when did god giue Idolators leaue to make miniſters.</p>
            <p>Seing therefore that popiſh prieſts are no miniſters, I ſee no ſhew of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie wherevpon my fayth, or the faith of any can be aſſured to receiue true baptiſme at their hands: vnleſſe it can be ſhewed by you, M. <hi>Some,</hi> that eyther there may bee fayth where there is no promiſe, or that there is a promiſe to receaue a ſacrament where there is no miniſter, which no man of any chriſtian modeſtie wil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. Hence alſo it followeth, that neyther the obſtinate crue of recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants in this land, who offer their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be profaned by trayterous &amp; runnagate Ieſuits, nor any els within the body of the Romiſh Babylon, can aſſure themſelues that their children receiue the ſubſtaunce of baptiſme.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1295:12"/>My reaſons beſides that they are no miniſters, are theſe. And I deſire that they may be examined by you, good M. <hi>Some;</hi> where you muſt remember that I ſpeake not of that which hath bene done yeſterday, but of the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that may be had of that which to morow is to be done.</p>
            <p>Where there is no true chriſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto men can bee engraffed by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: There true baptiſme as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſubſtaunce cannot be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.3. gal. 3.27.</note> for what baptiſme is that, which is not an ingraffinge into the true Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But in popery there is no true chriſt, wherevnto men may be ingraffed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not the true Chriſte, who cyther will not,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.15.19.</note> or cannot ſatisfie the wrath of God for the ſinnes of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, without their merits,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.25.</note> and ſuch is the Chriſt profeſſed in popery and no other.</p>
            <p>Therefore men can not be aſſured to haue the ſubſtance of baptiſme in the popiſh Church.</p>
            <p>No man can aſſure himſelf to haue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1295:13"/>the ſubſtance of baptiſme out of the Churche, and that by thoſe that are without the Church, for then a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t might be had out of the Church, which were very impious and abſurd to be affirmed.</p>
            <p>But popery is out of the Churche, and ſo are all popiſh prieſts.</p>
            <p>Therefore no man can aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelt to haue the ſubſtance of baptiſm in popery by any popiſh prieſt.</p>
            <p>That there is no Churche at all in popery, and that al popiſh prieſts are out or the Church, beſids the former reaſons, this one doth further ſhewe, If there be a Churche in popery, or if all popiſhe prieſtes be not out of the Churche, then thoſe magiſtrates that haue ſeparated themſelues and their ſubiectes (and all others that made this ſeperation) from the Romiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as from that ſynagogue where ſaluation is not to be had, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, where there is no Churche, are ſchiſmatikes, to ſpeake the leaſt. Becauſe it is a ſchiſme to make this ſeparation from the Churche, deteſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1295:13"/>the corruptions thereof we may, but make ſuche a ſeparation from the Churche, wee ought not vnleſſe wee would be accounted ſchiſmatiks. But thoſe magiſtrates and their people, that made this ſeparation, are not ſchiſmatickes, becauſe in popery the foundation is ouerthrowen, You ſay in your booke (M, <hi>Some</hi>) page 33. that you could preſſe the argument of the magiſtracie againſt me very far; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you may or no, that ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered when I deale with the point, but this I am aſſured off, that in this point, you ſhalbe driuen either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the abſurditye, that baptiſme is to bee had out of the Churche in a companye eſtraunged from Chriſte, which I thinke you will not doe, or vrged ſo farre, as to the plaine breach of a ſtatute (which far be it from me) euen in the cauſe of treaſon. Will yee ſay that baptiſme may be had out of the Church:<note place="margin">13. Eliza. A ſtrange Church that hath not Chriſt for the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> the aſſertion is abſurd; or wil you hold that there is a church in popery? the aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is dangerous, and I haue prooued it falſe. It is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1295:14"/>becauſe it affirmeth our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates to be ſchiſmatiks,<note place="margin">My mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is onely to ſhew the danger, &amp; not to preſſe the fame.</note> inaſmuch as they haue ſeperated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church: I hope rather then you will fall in to eyther of theſe pointes, that you will grant me the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if men might be aſſured that they could haue the true ſubſtance of baptiſme in popery, then they ought not to keep their children from po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh baptiſme, if there were no other baptiſme in the world to be had. For men might come to their baptiſme and deteſt their corruptions, if it bee Gods baptiſme, as you M. <hi>Some</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it to be, page 20. And they can ad an edifying worde vnto the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: if the recitall of the wordes of inſtitution be an edifying worde, and that be ſufficient to make a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, both whiche you haue written, page 23.24. But men ought rather to keep their children vnbaptized, then to offer them to be profaned by popiſh baptiſme, both for the former rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and becauſe wee ought to haue no more felowſhip with papiſts in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1295:14"/>ſeruice of God, then with pagan Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. M. Caluin hath written other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in this point,<note place="margin">L. Zo. 'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 10.4.</note> therefore againe I appeale to the word.</p>
            <p>Seing therefore in popery there is no Church, no miniſtery, no Chriſte; ſeeing we ought in no caſe to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with papiſts in their religion, but to bee ſeparated from them, as from thoſe that are out of the church; and ſuch as are become a very filthy cage and neſt of vncleane and ſacriledgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Idolators: therefore alſo it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily followeth, that neither our popiſh recuſants, nor any elſe, offring their children to bee baptized in the popiſh ſynagogue, by thoſe polluted and vncleane prieſts; may aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that they can bee there perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of true baptiſme, as touchinge the ſubſtance of baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Nowe to the examination of your reaſon brought to prooue that they which were baptized in popery, haue rece iued true baptiſme. Your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion you muſt remember, I do not deny, though your reaſon prooueth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1295:15"/>not the ſame, which is thus framed.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer deliuer Gods baptiſm, they deliuer true baptiſme; but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſtes deliuer Gods baptiſme: therefore true baptiſme.</p>
            <p>You haue changed the concluſion from that which was done, vnto that whiche is done, but this ouerſight I omit the aſſumption you thus proue.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer baptiſe in the name, not of Pope or Idols, but of the holy Trinitie, they deliuer Gods baptiſm; but popiſhe prieſts do baptize in the name of the holy trinitie: therefore they deliuer Gods baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Your propoſition in this laſt ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, is moſt falſe, and ſuch as vpon the grant whereof, not onely the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with vnpreaching mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, might bee aduouched, but alſo Gods whole ordinaunce in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of his holy ſacramentes quite ouerthrowen. For if it were true that ther were no more required to make ſubſtantiall baptiſme (as you here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more) but to baptiſe in the name of the trinitie; then theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1295:15"/>abſurdities would follow ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That an Amalekite might deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer true circumciſion, as touching the ſubſtance. 2 That true baptiſm might bee adminiſtred vnto a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce not capable of baptiſme, but this odious inſtaunce I will not vrge. 3 That a woman, 4 That any man not being a miniſter, as a child of fiue yeares olde, a Turke or Iewe might deliuer true baptiſm as touching the ſubſtance. For theſe pronouncing the wordes of inſtitution, might reteine by your reaſon, the eſſential form of Chriſtes baptiſme, and ſo to vſe your owne wordes; they baptizing not in the name of Pope or of Idols, but of the holy trinitie, ſhould deliuer Gods baptiſm and not mans? if Gods bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, then true baptiſme I am ſure, in like manner, by this reaſon they ſhould be Catabaptiſtes, which denie men to be rightly baptized by Turks or women. I would be full ſorie that the errors of the Katabaptiſts or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtes, coulde not be confuted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1295:16"/>by you withe ſounder reaſons then this you haue brought; and I would be alſo ſorie that you ſhould defende ſuch abſurd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequents as I wil driue you whether you will or no, vnleſſe you reuoke (as I hope you will) that which you haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. pardone me I pray you. I deale as reuerently as I may with you, retaining the maieſtie of the cauſe I defend; and I deale not againſt you, but againſt an erroneous aſſertion, which I now leaue; deſiring you very earneſtly, that you woulde conſider how vnreuerently the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God in the holy ſacraments is dealt with when the ſame is made to depend vpon the pronouncing of a few ſyllables, without any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration eyther of the perſon who is to adminiſter, or of the ſubſtantiall forme of conſecration contained in the expoſition of the holy inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of baptiſme, and the inuocation of the name of God, al which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of baptiſme, and could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be in Aegypt, where all was and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1295:16"/>couered vnder the darkneſſe of a ſtrange tongue. Your diſtinction that popiſh prieſts haue a calling, though a faltie, is a begging of the queſtion. For as I haue ſhewed, popiſh prieſtes haue no calling at all in the Church, and therefore how can they ſit in the chaire of the miniſterie? Is there a miniſtery out of the Church, Caiphas his prieſthood commeth afterwarde to bee conſidered of. The ſeconde point is to be handled next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That vnpreaching miniſters are no miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are affirmed to bee no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, not becauſe they are euill mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but becauſe their miniſterye is an euill and profane mininiſtery: So that in this pointe the faulte is not found with the euil miniſter, but with the euill miniſtery. Their miniſtery is profane and euill, becauſe there is no mention made of it in the word. And a miniſterye not mentioned in the worde is no miniſtery but a profane conſtitution. For the Lorde hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſet downe euerye miniſterie of the new teſtament, that ſhould be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1295:17"/>in the Church vnto the worlds ende;<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.11</note> wheras he hath not once mentioned the miniſtery of our readers, becauſe it is not a preaching miniſterye. The ſumme of this whole controuerſie is contayned in theſe three axiomes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Euery miniſtery is expreſſely ſet downe in the word.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.7.8. 1. Cor. 42.28. rom. 10.14. 1. Cor. 1.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Euery miniſtery of the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is a preaching miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The miniſtery of our vnpreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miniſters, is not a preaching mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterye.</p>
            <p>If you can ſhewe eyther of theſe 3. points to be falſe, I am ouerthrowne, if neyther, you muſt yeeld. The truth of all three, I haue ſhewed out of the word, in the laſt edition of my book. The two former are confirmed by the places quoted on the margent, the latter I will briefly prooue by theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 If the miniſtery of vnpreaching miniſters be a preaching miniſterye, or if their function be a paſtorall or doctorall function, then there had bene a preaching miniſtery, a paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1295:17"/>and doctorall function known in the Church, though there neuer had bene anye preacher therein. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, howe can their miniſterye bee a preaching miniſtery, or their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee a paſtorall function, whereas the ſame may bee in the Churche, no preaching miniſtery or paſtorall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction beeing knowne there? But no Churche, much leſſe a miniſtery had there beene knowne, if there neuer had bene any that coulde haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; becauſe God ordained the ſaints and ſo a Churche, onely to be gathered together by preaching or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, but not by the miniſtery of readers, becauſe it might haue bene in the world, and yet no ſaint gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby; which thing experience in our Churche prooueth to bee to true.</p>
            <p>My 2. and 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaſons are drawn out of theſe words of Paule, Rom. 13.6.7.8. Seeing then that wee haue giftes that are diuers, acording to the grace that is giuen vnto vs; whether wee haue propheſie, let vs propheſie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1295:18"/>to the proportion of fayth; or an office, let vs wait on the office; or hee that teacheth on teaching, or he that exhorteth on exhorting, &amp;c. the 2. reaſon is thus concluded.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer hath receiued a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye, and ſo a paſtorall or doctorall function, he hath receiued propheſie ſpoken of in this place, verſe 6. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery paſtoral or doctorall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, mencioned in the 7. &amp; 8. verſe, vnder theſe words: he that teacheth, hee that exhorteth; are contained vnder the word propheſie. verſe 6. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as he that hath not receiued that propheſie there ſet down, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is ment the interpretation of the worde; he hath not receiued the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall or doctoral function ſet down verſ. 7.8. But vnpreaching miniſters haue not receiued the propheſie ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in this place, which is expreſly ſet downe, verſe 6. to bee one of the diuers gifts beſtowed for the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body, which is the church. Therefore alſo, they haue receiued neither a paſtorall nor a doctorall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1295:18"/>function, and ſo no preaching mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye.</p>
            <p n="3">3 No miniſtery is ſeperated from a gift, becauſe propheſie ſpoken of in this 6. verſe, vnder which as we ſee, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery paſtorall and doctorall miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is contayned, can not bee ſeuered from a gift: but the miniſtery of our readers is ſeuered in them from a gyft: therefore in them it is no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
            <p>It is no miniſterye in them I ſay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that miniſterye, the generall name whereof they haue, is not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from a gift in preaching mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: but what is that to them? what is the miniſterye of other men vnto them? they are not miniſters, by the miniſtery wherewith other men are endued, but by their own, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeuered from a gifte, is no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. Paul had bene no Apoſtle, and had receiued no Apoſtleſlip, vnleſſe he coulde haue ſayde, I am a miniſter according vnto the grace giuen vnto me, Ephe. 3.7. and not according to the grace giuen vnto other Apoſtles:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1295:19"/>the generall name of whoſe Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I am entituled with. A ridiculous ſpeeche it were, to ſaye mine apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp hath receiued grace, but I that am the apoſtle haue receiued none.</p>
            <p>How then may our readers claime a preachinge miniſterye vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſeing the miniſtery which they challenge is altogether in them with out a gifte, though it be not ſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Euery vnpreaching miniſter ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in executing the works of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral function, as the ſacraments. &amp;c therefore he hath no miniſtery; and ſo nyether a paſtorall nor doctorall function. Hee hath no miniſtery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, his calling is not the calling of the miniſtery, his callinge is not the calling of the miniſterye, becauſe hee ſinneth in intermedlinge withe the workes thereof. And this is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible trueth, that no man ſinneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he dealeth with the workes of his calling. For this is the duety that God requireth at the hands of euery man. Manye ſinne in deede becauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1295:19"/>they walk corruptly in their callings, &amp; haue no care to glorifie God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Col. 3.17. But leaue thy corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and thou ſinneſt not, in keeping thee to the works of thy calling. The hypocrits in the daies of Iſayah. 1.13 ſinned not becauſe they offered ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but becauſe they did the ſame through hypocriſie. Their hypocriſie they ought to haue lefte, but not his ſeruice in ſacrificing according to his commaundement; but our readers though they ſhould with as little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and as great zeale to Gods glory and the good of his Churche as any men, deale in the workes of a paſtoral miniſtery, yet they ſhould ſtil do that which the Lord had forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to doe, whence it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that the works of the miniſtery are not the works of their caling. For God forbiddeth no man to deale therewith, &amp; not the being workes of their calling, they are no miniſters, and haue neyther paſtorall nor doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torall function.</p>
            <p n="5">5 This is farther ſhewed, foraſmuch
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1295:20"/>as the Lorde doeth not commit vnto bare reders the charge of thoſe ſouls, ouer whom they are, which he doth vnto euerye one that hath a paſtorall function, Acts. 20.16.28. 1, theſ. 5.12 Heb. 13.17. For to what ende elſe, ſhould he commit a miniſterye vnto anye, who haue ſoules vnder their charge? The Church indeed may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſouls of men vnto reders, but certainly the Lord committeth none vnto them. And he is no miniſter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom the Lorde doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mite this charge, as the places before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted do ſhew. For the Lord hath in his word, ordained not onely offices, the executors whereof ſhoulde haue the ouerſight of ſoules, but alſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were to execute thoſe fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. 1. Cor. 12.28. 1. Pet. 4.10. rom 12.6.7.8. Epheſ. 4.7.11. Now vnprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching miniſters are non of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe the Lorde knoweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to bee able to feede ſoules. And let not men bee ſo iniurious vnto the Lorde, as to affirme, that hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto his reuealed ordinance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1295:20"/>(for therof I ſpeke as of a miniſtery, &amp; not of his ſecret iudgments) bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the ſoules of men to be ſtarued and kept from ſaluation, As hee muſt needes be conuinced to doe if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed them vnto thoſe men, the diſpenſation of whoſe miniſtery is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beget none, feede none, ſaue none. you muſt vnderſtande againe, that I ſpeake of the miniſtery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by readers are miniſters, that is of their owne, and not of the miniſtery whereby preaching miniſters are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, wherewith readers haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer howe can the Lorde bee ſaide to commit the charge of ſoules according to his owne reuealed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, vnto thoſe who may truely obiect vnto him, that he dealeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuriouſly with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by exacting thoſe thinges to bee perfourmed at their handes and in their owne perſons, as neceſſary duties of their callings, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the performaunce whereof, they haue receiued no abilitie from him. Is man to bee aunſwerable vnto the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1295:21"/>Lorde of that which he neuer recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? doth the Lorde require the vſe of that tallent which hee neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed? doth he laye that vpon any, whereof hee may haue iuſte cauſe to complaine? when did hee impoſe a charge vpon any, vnto whom he gaue not gifts to diſcharge the ſame? now the charge of ſoules whiche he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth vnto anye, hee requireth at their handes vnto whom he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it, which he could not doe, if hee had not giuen abilitie to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof.</p>
            <p>What then? ſhall ignoraunt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be free from the blood of ſouls, in aſmuch as the lord neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted any ſoule vnto their charge. It were well with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore men, if the caſe ſo ſtood. But alas it is not ſo. And yet the cauſe of their deſtruction procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not from their vnfaithfulneſſe in the diſcharge of that vocation whiche hee hath allotted vnto them, but it commeth iuſtly vpon them, in that they haue deſperatly thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiues contrary vnto Gods reuealed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1295:21"/>will, vpon thoſe men with the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of whoſe ſoules God neuer tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſuch as they are. The Lord ſayth vnto them, intrude your ſeiues and you will, vnto the places of paſtors, and ſo enforce me to bring heauy &amp; ſwift damnation vpon you: but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I wil bequeath no ſoule vnto your cuſtodye. They on the other ſide in their practiſe ſay, Lord whether thou committeſt vnto vs any charge of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoule or no, wee care not, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then wee ſhoulde not haue the meanes to liue in this life, (for this is their onely ſcope in continuinge in the miniſterye) require the blood of ſoules, and what thou wilte at our hands. And ſo ſenſeles men, they ſell them-ſelues, body and ſoule vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting wo and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The pretence that the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the chardge of ſoules vnto their miniſtery, and not vnto them, is firſt a deſiring of that in queſtion; (for they are denyed to haue any miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) and otherwiſe many wais vnſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. 1 Becauſe the Lord commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1295:22"/>not the charge of ſoules there, where the puniſhement of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction cannot take holde, as it can not vpon the miniſtery:<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 2 the miniſtry is but a dead thing of it ſelf; moſt beautifull in deed, as being an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lorde, but able to ſaue none, vnleſſe it be committed vnto a perſon, who in the execution therof, is able to ſhew himſelf to be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God for that glorious worke. This is taught Epheſ. 4. where the Apoſtle verſes 6 and 7. hauing ſpoken of the giftes beſtowed vpon men for this miniſteriall work, aſcribeth verſ. 11.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the gathering together of the ſayntes, not vnto the giftes or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but vnto men endued with the ſayde giftes. For he doth not ſay that the Lord hath appointed for the gathering together of the ſaynts, an apoſtleſhipp , a paſtorall or doctorall function, &amp;c. but that he ordained apoſtles, paſtors, &amp;c. for that end and purpoſe; whereunto becauſe our readers were not appoynted, it forcibly enſueth that they haue no miniſtery,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1295:22"/>no paſtorall or doctorall function, and ſo are no miniſters: which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo in the laſt edition of mine Exhortation vnto my countrimen, I haue enforced by manye ſtrong and as I am aſſured inuincible reaſons, drawne out of the infallible trueth of Gods worde. I woulde intreate yon M. <hi>Some,</hi> when you haue anſwered the reaſons I haue nowe ſet downe to anſwere alſo, the 1.2.3. and 25. rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I haue there vſed. For you ſhall but ſtriue in vayne againſt the concluſion, as long as the premiſes whereby it is inferred remaine firme. If the reader woulde be further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in this poynte concerning the dumbe miniſtery, he is to be referred vnto that which in the aforeſaid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe I haue ſet downe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Nowe to the concluſion, If vnprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching miniſters be no miniſters, and if I cannot be aſſured to receiue a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but onely at the hands of a miniſter; both which you ſee M. <hi>Some</hi> to be prooued by me, then cannot I aſſure my ſelfe, that an vnpreaching
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1295:23"/>miniſter can deliuer a ſacrament vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: and therefore it is vnlawfull for me or any chriſtian to go vnto an vnpreaching miniſter for the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; if vnlawfull, then a ſinne, if a ſin, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the godly are polluted which goe vnto them for the ſacramentes: you know (M. <hi>Some</hi>) what I meane by an vnpreaching miniſter; namely, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one learned or vnlearned, that cannot ſhewe him-ſelfe by the good trial of his gifts, to haue that fitnes to teach, whereof we read. 2. tim. 2.2.1. tim. 3.3. which ability the Lord doth not ordinarily beſtowe vpon any in theſe our dayes, without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the artes, eſpecially the two handmaydes of all learninge, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricke and Logick, and the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall tongues wherein the worde was written. And therefore I am as farre from accounting the vnskilfull preachers, which ſpeake hand ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, they care not what; againſte whom your complaint is very iuſt to be miniſters, as I am from acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging many of our abſurd doctors
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1295:23"/>to be apt to teach, who can bring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into the pulpit, but that which other men haue written, and that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often, ſo fit to the purpoſe, of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as the reaſon from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to the ſtaffe, is ſoundly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In theſe three ſortes of ſuppoſed miniſters (and there could be a fourth added vnto them) conſiſteth the woe of our Church.</p>
            <p>The reſt of your booke is nowe to be examined. Your concluſion, page 22. that they which were baptized by vnpreching miniſters, are rightly bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized as touching the ſubſtaunce of baptiſme; I do not gainſay. Your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are weake. For how coulde wee proue your concluſion, if men ſhould denie popiſh baptiſm to be true bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as I do not you know &amp; he ſhuld do me great iniurie, which would lay that to my charge. Were it ſufficient for vs to ſay they were Katabaptiſtes which denie popiſhe baptiſme? How could this be proued? and this ſhould not prooue the matter doubted off. Shall wee ſaye that they ſinne, in not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1295:24"/>preſenting themſelues to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. To whome ſhoulde they preſent themſelues? who would baptize the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Admit they ſinned in receauing the Lords Supper before they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, ſhould they therefore bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of the comfort of baptiſme? to affirme that this weare a goinge backward, is no reaſon, becauſe they were perſwaded that they had bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, otherwiſe they would not haue beene ſo farr on their iourney, vntill they had beene accompanied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. But they omitted baptiſme of ignorance and not of contemt: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they denie the receiuing of the Lordes ſupper to haue bene a ſinne, anye more then it woulde be a ſinne in them nowe to receiue the Lordes ſupper, if they coulde not haue bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Baptiſme they woulde haue, if they coulde orderlye come by the ſame. Becauſe men will bee ſo iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto them, as to denie them the comfort of baptiſme which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue, ſhould they denie to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the comfort of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1295:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>which they may haue? Ye, but no vncircumciſed might eate the paſcall lambe. Exod. 12.48. True; But what ſhall we ſay vnto thoſe that were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed in the wilderneſſe fortie yeres almoſt. Ioſh. 5.5. Did they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eate the paſſeouer all that time? If they did, the place of Exodus will be quickly anſwered. It is plaine that the paſſeouer was celebrated in the wildernes once at the leaſt. Nom. 9.1, If euery yeare, why ſhould the godly of the family be excluded from the family be excluded from the action, the cauſe why they were vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed not being in them. None vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed might miniſter before the altar. True, but did non of the Leuits that were borne in the wilderneſſe teach Iaacob the law, or offer the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of his God in all thoſe fourtye yeares?</p>
            <p>Thus many thinges you ſee might be obiected againſt your reaſons, &amp; I take the obiections to bee of ſome waight, It had bin well you had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of them before you had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1295:25"/>your booke. And the baptiſme by vnpreaching miniſters, muſt haue better prooffes then anye you haue brought as yet, or elſe I feare me, our poſterities will not be ſatisfied ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>Your next reaſon, page 23. is ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Readers pronounce the wordes of inſtitution with the deliuerie of the element, therfore ſaye you they deliuer a ſacrament: you haue once already alledged this to prooue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh baptiſme, page 20. I haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it page 29. 30. 31. And the place of Matth. 28.29. brought in by you page 23. proueth your conſequent to bee falſe. For it ſheweth that he who is to baptiſe, muſt bee alſo able to teache, which abilitie is wanting in our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Go ſayth our Sauiour, and teach all nations, baptizing, &amp;c. Therefore if he that deliuereth the element bee not able to teach, we cannot be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it is a ſacrament. Becauſe the commandement is not generally to all that could pronounce the wordes of inſtitution, beeing thereunto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1295:25"/>by the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the time, but perticularly limited vnto them that can teache, vnleſſe you will ſaye, that the Lorde biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go teach, who cannot teach whiche were not once to be concerned of his maieſtie. The corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, that the deliuery of the element ſhold be ſeuered from the preaching of the word, is a breach of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, you cannot deny, Matth. 28 19. act. 20.7. and therefore vngodly and intollerable. Whether it mak the action fruſtrate or no, that is not the queſtion.</p>
            <p>Your 3. reaſon pag. 24. is this.</p>
            <p>Vnpreaching miniſters do ad an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying word vnto the element, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a ſacramente. This reaſon is the ſame with the former, which ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the great nakednes and pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the cauſe, that one reaſon muſt be thriſe periured to proue the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of it, which notwithſtanding it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſhew. I deny the antecedent, &amp; conſequent. Your reaſon of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent, that the recitall of the ſum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1295:26"/>of Chriſts Sermon that is, the wordes of inſtitution is an edifying worde is falſe, and maintaineth charming. For do you thinke that the worde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, being as you ſay, the ſumm of Chriſtes Sermon, is then an edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word, whenſoeuer it is recited by a profane perſon, euen in the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Gods ordinance? Looke 2. tim. 4.3. and you ſhall finde that the worde barely reade, and to no other purpoſe then to edifie by reading, is not wholeſome doctrine. The popiſh prieſte eyther without or, within the booke, pronounceth in his darke La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, the ſumm of Chriſtes Sermon, is that an edifying word, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely breatheth. The worde of God vttered, is not an edifying worde, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it be vttered according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, both in regarde of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that vtter the ſame, and the end wherefore it is vttered. No learned man will denie the Lordes prayer rightly ſayd to be an edifying worde. And yet by your leaue, no learned man vnleſſe he fauoreth charming or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1295:26"/>popery, will ſay that the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pronounced by an ignorant man, in a ſtrange tongue , or profaned by a witch, is an edifying word.</p>
            <p>Concerning your conſequent, doe you thinke that euerye one that can ad an edifying word vnto the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, may miniſter a ſacrament? it is not ſo. For Paul requireth the words of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery chriſtian (wemen &amp; al) to be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying wordes, Eph. 4.29. euen in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon talk. Shal therefore the element adminiſtred by euerye chriſtian be a ſacrament? God forbid. And yet eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chriſtian can ad the ſum of Chriſts ſermon vnto the element in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the ſupper; which if it were ſufficient, as by your reaſon it is, then wemen, children, &amp;c. idiots that coulde not read might deliuer a ſacrament.</p>
            <p>The reaſon concluding vnpreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miniſters to be non, becauſe they are not apt to teache, you haue twiſe repeated within one twelue lines, pag 24.25. and made two ſeuerall obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof. That was an ouerſight:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1295:27"/>The ſufficiencie of the argument, I haue ſhewed to be ſuche, as Caiphas his miniſtery, and Herods magiſtracy brought in by you, pag. 25. 26. will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aunſwer the ſame. Both of them with the reaſon from the outwarde calling of readers, pag. 25. I referre to your next chapter, where they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated: thyther nowe I am come, where the contradictorie of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſhall be ſet downe and prooued briefly; becauſe the nullitie of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching miniſtery, may be in ſteede of a 1000. reaſons to proue the ſame. By pollution, doubt not, you meane ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The godly do ſinne, vvhich do communicate vvith vnpreaching miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe 1. they communicate with thoſe who are no miniſters. 2. they cannot be aſſured to receiue a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at their hands. 3 they do not examine them-ſelues aright, and ſo are not worthy receiuers, 1. Cor. 11.28. inaſmuch as they do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg it a ſinne to communicat where there is no miniſter. 4. becauſe they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1295:27"/>eyther make the element to bee a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament naturally in it ſelfe, and not by the ordinance of God, or els think the ordinance of God in the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſacrament onely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the recitall of the words; I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thee, &amp;c. or rake eate, &amp;c, wheras a miniſter is a moſt principall part of the ordinance. 5 Becauſe they make the ſacraments to be marks no more eſtentiall vnto the Church, then to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther idolatrous ſynagogues. For the element may be deliuered out of the Church by a publike perſon, euen as ſubſtantially, as by our mere readers. 6 They approoue the ſin of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching miniſtery. Laſtly, becauſe they are perſwaded, that Chriſt doth deliuer vnto them the ſeales or their ſaluation, by the hands of thoſe that are not miniſters; to wit, by vnprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching readers. In al which points, the godly ſinne, and therefore are pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in communicating with vnprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching miniſters. Nowe let vs ſee howe you haue proued the contrary.</p>
            <p>Where the reader muſt againe be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1295:28"/>put in minde, that I you haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nothing vnleſſe the queſtion bee graunted vnto you: and 2 that your reaſons are repeated too often.</p>
            <p>The miniſters ignorance ſaye you, page 28. cannot peruert Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: and againe, page 29. the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes are not the worſe for the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the miniſter, &amp;c. All this I grant, but bare readers are not mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the doubt is, whether the action performed by them be the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God, whether it be a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Theſe be the queſtions which you ought to haue prooued, and not haue taken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as principles, though you do this: the 3 and 4 time, pag 28. line 6. and 24.</p>
            <p>M.D. <hi>Some,</hi> pag. 28. the worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker receiues a bleſsing, if a bleſsing no pollution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Penri;</hi> firſt it is doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may be aſſured that it is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; 2 he is no worthye recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that receiueth of an Idoll mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: 3 there may be a bleſsing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; yet pollution in the receiuer:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1295:28"/>Looke 2. Chronic. 30.17.18.19. Nom. 9.7. The obiection concerning the giuer &amp; the receiuer, in your 31. pa. was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mine: I coulde turne it againſt you, but I muſt be briefe.</p>
            <p>Concerning the nullity of our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders miniſtery, we are to knowe that there is a nullitie of a miniſterye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; eyther becauſe the action proceedeth from a corrupt miniſter, as pſalm. 50.16. whom God would not haue to deale with his ordinances, or from a corrupt and euill miniſterye, which is none of Gods ordinaunce. The action of the former is ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall in regard of vs, of the latter wee know no ſubſtance it can haue. Of the former there is a nullitie onely in the ſight of God; of the latter, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Lorde and alſo of vs. The nullitie of our readers miniſtery is of this latter ſorte, namely ſuche as we ought in no wiſe to account a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. Whereas therefore you graunt that there is a nullity of our readers miniſtery before God, and yet affirm them to be miniſters, you ſwarue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:1295:29"/>the point, and ſo your anſwere, page 31. Is nothinge to the purpoſe, but a deſiring of the queſtion after your vſuall manner. As Caiphas then, and the reſt of the ſleepye dogges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the prophet cryeth out,<note place="margin">Iſa. 56.9.</note> were wicked men, God woulde not haue ſuch to be his miniſters: hyther refer Iſa. 1.13. but as they had the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery which God allowed of, they were miniſters vnto the people. This miniſtery, our readers want, therfore they can be miniſters, neither in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ier. 29.31. Zac. 14.14.29.9. Zach 13.5. Iere. 29.25. There is a difference betweene the nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the miniſter, and the nullity of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</note> nor of the Church. Shemaiah was a wicked man, and a falſe prophet, ſo were the reſt of his ſtamp. The Lord deteſted both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; their miniſtery. Zephania &amp; Caiphas hie prieſts with their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, were as wicked as any of the falſe prophetes, the Lord abhorred the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but their miniſtery was his ordinance.</p>
            <p>Hence M. <hi>Some,</hi> it followeth, that neyther the bribery of your Caiphas, nor the blindenes of your ignoraunt Leuites, can make ſuche a nullitie of their prieſthood, as they ſhould be no
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1295:29"/>prieſtes vnto the people. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great reaſon whie the parentes of our ſauiour, &amp; the reſt of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereof you ſpeake. page 28, 19. ſhould not leaue the ſeruice of God for the pollution of the prieſtes. Iſai ſpeaketh againſt blind watchmen, 56 10, but chap. 42.19.20. It ſhal appear that they ſaw many things, but kept them not, I pray you confer the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and it can neuer be prooued that any of them were ſo blinde, as they could not declare by preachinge the generall vſe of the ſacrifices and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Their wants might be many but not like the inſufficiency of our readers. Beit they were as inſufficient yet their miniſtery might be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnfitnes to teach, made not a nullitie of the Leuiticall prieſts office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe 1 it was ſufficient to make him a lawfull, though not a good prieſt,<note place="margin">Nom. 3.10 Leuit. 8. Exo. 29.</note> for him to be of the line of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: 2 there was no commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t concerning the tryall of his fitnes to teach: 3 It is not mentioned that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1295:30"/>any were put from the priſthood for want of this ability, wheras the dout whether they were the ſonnes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron. Ezra. 2.63. and their idolatry, 2. Chron. bereaued them thereof;<note place="margin">Act. 21.26.</note> 4 the example of Paule confirmeth this, who communicated ſince his conuerſion with thoſe priſts that wer as vnlearned as euer anye; whiche he woulde not haue done if inability to teach, had made them no prieſts.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore M. <hi>Some</hi> to make your argument from the Leuiticall prieſthood to bee forcible. For your vnpreching miniſters, you muſt proue that either our readers miniſtery is a Leuiticall miniſtery, that the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance therof is vnder the new couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſhew that the corrupt aprobation, for ſo I name the beſt outwarde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling they can haue of the Churche, is as forcible to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſters, as was the ordinaunce of God to make the ſons of Aaron ſacrificing at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem to be prieſts. Now,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the corrupt allovvance of the Church cannot make our readers to be ſubſtanciall miniſters</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:1295:30"/>
            <p>For ſo all men and wemen, without or within the Church might be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the miniſtery, becauſe all may be capable of this outward alowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; 2 and perticularly a man, not furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with naturall capacity; 3 a man that could not read, though he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo the gift of interpretation; for ſuche a one might recite the liturgie without the booke; 4 the Churche might make a man miniſter againſt his will, though he ſhould neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thervnto. And this is the willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that I meane, when I ſay that the inward caling is contained in the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of gifts, &amp; willingnes to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctize, which willingnes I gather vpon the wordes, <hi>Epith mei</hi> and <hi>oregetai,</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the A poſtle. Your reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the malicious Philippian miniſters, toucheth not the queſtion.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.1.</note> Thus Caiphas with his crue of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthye and monſtrous prieſts (who within a fewe pages, in your booke haue impudently ſo often troubled the reader) is anſwered. And I thinke it a great iudgment of God that the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1295:31"/>ornaments of our Engliſh and welch miniſtery, for the moſt part conſiſteth in the deformitie of ſuche lothſome ſpots.</p>
            <p>M.D. <hi>Some</hi> page 32. They of whoſe magiſtracie there is a nullitye before God, though they haue an outwarde calling, ought not to bee accounted magyſtrates. <hi>I.P.</hi> You demand what I thinke of this propoſition. Surely my iudgement is, that it is altogether without ſence, and ouerthroweth it ſelf. For it is as if you ſaid, he of whoſe fayth there is a nullitye before God, though he be aſſured of his ſaluation is not to be accounted a faythful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Why? to be aſſured of ſaluation, &amp; to haue a nullitie of fayth before God, cannot ſtand together. No more can the outward calling of the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſtand with the nullity thereof. For the outwarde calling maketh a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There be three eſſentiall differences betvveene an euill magiſtrate and a reading miniſter</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The outwarde calling of an euill magiſtrate, maketh him a ſubſtantial
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1295:31"/>magiſtrate, ſo cannot the outward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of readers make them to be miniſters. 2 The magiſtracie of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill magiſtrate, may be allowable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, ſo cannot the miniſtery of readers. 3 Men may bee aſſured to receiue that accordinge to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God ſubſtantially at the handes of an euill magiſtrate, which concerneth them to haue from him, ſo can they not of a bare reader; For there is no man that can aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be pertaker of a ſubſtantiall ſacrament, at the hands of ſuch, and preache they cannot. I haue handled this poynte of the magiſtracie in my former booke, from page 47. to 51.</p>
            <p>But M. <hi>Some,</hi> where is that reaſon which you could preſſe ſo far? is this it? they of whoſe magiſtracie there is a nullity before God, ought not to be accounted magiſtrates. I ſay your propoſition is true, aſſume what you wil, you know what maner of nullity I meane.</p>
            <p>My reaſon concluding the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of communicatinge with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1295:32"/>hauing but an outward calling: becauſe it is a ſinne to communicate with them, whiche onely want the ſame hauing fitnes to teache, is ſuch as I can not but maruell that you would thinke it could bee anſwered by a deſiring of the queſtion, which is a fault in reaſoninge, wherein be like you ſeeme to take delight; you ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that readers deliuer a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. How can we be ſure thereof, &amp; why may not I ſay as well, that a man indued with giftes to teach, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer a ſacrament, though he haue no outwarde calling, whiche aſſertion would be falſe. By an extraordinarye ſacrament, I meane baptiſme or the Lords ſupper, adminiſtred either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly by a miniſter, or any way by on that is no miniſter. I neuer affirmed, the elements deliuered by readers to be ſacraments. It is one thing not to deny them, another thing to affirme them to be ſacraments; the former I haue written, the latter I neuer did; &amp; they doe my writinges great iniurie, that report the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:1295:32"/>
            <p>Thus M. <hi>Some</hi> I haue run through the pointes in your booke that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned me, I haue beene driuen to deale briefly therein. I had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I am inforced to ende, and to omit that, which page 9. line 11. I promiſed to handle in the latter end, with diuers other I haue not the like libertie for printing that you M. <hi>Some</hi> doe inioy. Let me but haue the fauor to bee iudicially heard according to the word, and I will perſonally vpon the perill of my life, defend theſe two points againſt all men. I am ſory that you whom I reuerence, ſhould be the inſtrument to oppugne a trueth. The Lord reſpect the cauſe of his owne glorie, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our ſinne. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 1. line 20. &amp; 23. for 2. read 3. pag, 47. line 14. blot out, family be excluded from the</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
